<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly psalme of Marye Queene which brought vs comfort al, through God, whom wee of dewtye prayse, that giues her foes a fal. By Rychard Beeard. Anno domini. 1553.</title>
            <author>Beeard, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1553</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112243</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847501</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847501</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12538</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06091)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12538)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 486:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly psalme of Marye Queene which brought vs comfort al, through God, whom wee of dewtye prayse, that giues her foes a fal. By Rychard Beeard. Anno domini. 1553.</title>
                  <author>Beeard, Richard.</author>
                  <author>Bownell, Thomas. Godly psalme in meetre.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fleetestrete, at the sygne of the faucon against saint Donstons Church by [J. Kingston for] Wylliam Griffith: and are to be solde at his shoppe a lytle aboue the conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1553]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The 1st psalm has music in 4 parts--STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes: "A godly psalme in meetre" by Thomas Bownell.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Trinity College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12538:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12538:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Godly Pſalme, of Marye Queene, which brought vs comfort al, Through God, whom wee of dewtye prayſe, that giues her foes a fal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Rychard Beeard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno domini.</hi> 1553.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in Fleeteſtrete, at the ſygne of the Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con againſt ſaint Donſtons Church by Wylliam Griffith: and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe a lytle aboue the Conduit.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="music">
            <pb facs="tcp:12538:2"/>
            <div n="medius" type="part">
               <head>Medius,</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>Al England now bee glad at ones w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one heart mynde, and voyce: for now haue wee the greateſt cauſe to ſyng &amp; eke reioyce to ſyng &amp; eke reioyce.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="contratenor" type="part">
               <head>Contratenor.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>Al England now bee glad at ones, with one heart mynde &amp; voice: For now haue wee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt cauſe the greateſt cauſe to ſyng and eke reioyce.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="tenor" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12538:2"/>
               <head>Tenor.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>Al England now bee glad at ones, with one heart mynde and voice: for now haue wee the greateſt cauſe the greateſt cauſe to ſyng and eke reioyce to ſyng &amp; eke reioyce.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="bassus" type="part">
               <head>Baſſus.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>Al England now bee glad at ones w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one heart mynde &amp; voyce: for now haue wee the greateſt cauſe the greateſt cauſe to ſyng and eke reioyce to ſyng and eke reioyce.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="metrical_Psalm_of_Queen_Mary_I">
            <pb facs="tcp:12538:3"/>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L England now bee glad at ones,</l>
               <l>With one heart mynde and voyce:</l>
               <l>For now haue wee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt cauſe</l>
               <l>To ſing and eke reioyce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2</head>
               <l>For God hath brought his ſeruaunts trew</l>
               <l>From troubles ſore and great,</l>
               <l>Put downe the proude, &amp; hathe the meeke</l>
               <l>In theyr iuſt places ſet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3</head>
               <l>¶ The Lord hathe turnd his wrath and ire,</l>
               <l>From vs, out of hys mynde:</l>
               <l>Beeholding vs with countenaunce</l>
               <l>Moaſt louing ſweete and kynde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4</head>
               <l>☞ That God which might haue rightwiſely,</l>
               <l>Deſtroyde vs euery one,</l>
               <l>Hathe ſhewd him ſelf moaſt mercyful,</l>
               <l>To healp vs al alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5</head>
               <l>☞ He hathe regarded equitie,</l>
               <l>Treuth, iuſtice, law, and right:</l>
               <l>And ouerthrowne and vanquiſſhed</l>
               <l>The wrongful dealers might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6</head>
               <l>¶ Wee looked al for peſtilence</l>
               <l>And vengeaunce at his hand,</l>
               <l>And eke innumerable plagues</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12538:3"/>
               <l>To come vpon the land:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>7</head>
               <l>¶ But nowe hathe hee ſent downe his grace</l>
               <l>And mercy from aboue,</l>
               <l>And ſhewed vs vndoubtedly</l>
               <l>A token of his loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>8</head>
               <l>¶ Wee haue ful iuſtly looked heeare</l>
               <l>For death and ruines rife.</l>
               <l>And now doo wee beehold and truſt</l>
               <l>A good and ioyful lyfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>9</head>
               <l>¶ Yea, wee that weare moaſt ſorowful,</l>
               <l>Without a ſpreet or heart:</l>
               <l>Within a quarter of an houre</l>
               <l>Did quicken and reuert.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>10</head>
               <l>¶ Wee which weare brought by ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</l>
               <l>Vntrewth and wronge tobey:</l>
               <l>Do trewth and iuſtice execute,</l>
               <l>And put that wrong away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>11</head>
               <l>¶ Wee for our owne great variaunce</l>
               <l>Did forayne ſtraungers feare,</l>
               <l>Leſt they throughe oure diſcenſion heare</l>
               <l>Might rule among vs beare:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <head>12</head>
               <l>¶ But now wee ſhal with vnytie</l>
               <l>Bee able to withſtand,</l>
               <l>And vanquiſh al our enemies,</l>
               <l>And driue ſuch from oure land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <pb facs="tcp:12538:4"/>
               <head>13</head>
               <l>¶ Oure kyngdome which deuyded ſo</l>
               <l>Could neuer long abyde:</l>
               <l>ſhall now in vnitie bee kept,</l>
               <l>And treaſon bee eſpide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <head>14</head>
               <l>¶ And wee that onely looked for</l>
               <l>Gods vengeaunce to vs bent:</l>
               <l>Haue now his greateſt benefyte</l>
               <l>Whiche hee to vs hathe ſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>15</head>
               <l>¶ Hee doothe beehold vs meryli,</l>
               <l>And wil continew ſtyl,</l>
               <l>Yf wee as ſeruauntes to his trewth,</l>
               <l>Obey vnto his wyl.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <head>16</head>
               <l>¶ Hee ſaw that wickedneſſe aroſe,</l>
               <l>And bare his trewth deſpite:</l>
               <l>And now wil hee out of the land</l>
               <l>Deſtroy the workers quite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <head>17</head>
               <l>¶ When tyme that none durſt ſpeake for trewth,</l>
               <l>Then hee him ſelfe, ſo good</l>
               <l>Hathe ſtepped foorth, and opend al,</l>
               <l>Tauenge the gyltleſſe bloude.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <head>18</head>
               <l>¶ He ſetteth and eſtablyſſheth</l>
               <l>His ſeruauntes in their right:</l>
               <l>And ouerthrowes the wicked ſort,</l>
               <l>For al theyr ſtrength and might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
               <head>19</head>
               <l>¶ It is not armoure, harneyſe bright,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12538:4"/>
               <l>Nor any weapon ſtrong,</l>
               <l>The ſtrength that to the handes of men,</l>
               <l>Or hoorſes dothe belong:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>02</head>
               <l>¶ Nor any power on the earth</l>
               <l>That can preuayle or ſtand,</l>
               <l>But onely God the Lord him ſelf</l>
               <l>Wil haue the vpperhand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <head>21</head>
               <l>¶ What can a fortreſſe, caſtel ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Or bulwarke els preuayle:</l>
               <l>Againſt the Lorde that maketh al?</l>
               <l>In neede theeſe thinges wyl fayle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <head>22</head>
               <l>¶ The lord beeholdes the hearts and myndes</l>
               <l>Of godly men ful playne,</l>
               <l>Whiche onely ſeeke that ryghtwyſeneſſe</l>
               <l>And equitie may raygne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <head>23</head>
               <l>¶ How wonderſly doothe God with vs</l>
               <l>His people England deale?</l>
               <l>Suche ioy as wee ſcarce looked for</l>
               <l>Among vs to reueale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <head>24</head>
               <l>¶ Hee healps y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> captiues out of priſon,</l>
               <l>Breakes the walles of ſtone:</l>
               <l>And riddes his choſen from the death,</l>
               <l>And peryls euery one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <head>25</head>
               <l>Oure comfort is come neare, and eke</l>
               <l>Oure prayer heard, I truſt:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12538:5"/>
               <l>Of God which in the heauen dwelles,</l>
               <l>And fyghteth for the iuſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
               <head>26</head>
               <l>¶ For hee hathe ſet and ſtablyſſhed,</l>
               <l>Oure worthy ſoueraygne:</l>
               <l>And oure liege Lady, Marie Queene,</l>
               <l>On vs by trewth to raygne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="27">
               <head>27</head>
               <l>¶ Hee hathe vs ſent a comforter,</l>
               <l>To bee oure healp and guyde:</l>
               <l>With pitie and with vertues al</l>
               <l>Endewd on euery ſyde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <head>28</head>
               <l>¶ The lawful, iuſt, and rightuouſe,</l>
               <l>Of England, head, and Queene:</l>
               <l>To bee the true enheritoure,</l>
               <l>As hathe her brother beene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
               <head>29</head>
               <l>Not clayming by colluſion,</l>
               <l>Nor cloking it by ſleyght:</l>
               <l>But by her byrth, deſcending from</l>
               <l>Her godly father ſtreight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30">
               <head>30</head>
               <l>¶ She beeing eldeſt ſiſter right</l>
               <l>Vnto oure ſoueraigne Lord,</l>
               <l>Kynge Edward late the ſyxt by name,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſtrength was gods trew word.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="31">
               <head>31</head>
               <l>For which moaſt godly impe &amp; bud</l>
               <l>Of Ieſſees ſtocke and roote,</l>
               <l>Thoughe wee haue almooſt cauſe to ſighe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12538:5"/>
               <l>And ſorow bee oure boote:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Yet are wee comforted agayne,</l>
               <l>Lyft vp, and eke erect:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ycauſe the Lord hathe placed thus</l>
               <l>His choſen and elect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
               <l>¶ Whiche beeing oure moaſt godly Queene,</l>
               <l>That ſeekes our preſeruacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</l>
               <l>No doubt wil ſtrongly buyld vpon</l>
               <l>Her brothers good fondacion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34">
               <head>34</head>
               <l>¶ The ground worke hee hathe layde him ſelfe,</l>
               <l>And ſhee is left a lon,</l>
               <l>To buyld the houſe, and fortreſſe vp</l>
               <l>Of trew religion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
               <head>35</head>
               <l>¶ O England now continew ſtyl,</l>
               <l>In myrth and ioy therfore:</l>
               <l>For God wyl ſtrengthen day by day</l>
               <l>Your gladneſſe more and more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="36">
               <head>36</head>
               <l>Our ſoueraygne &amp; rightioyſe Queene</l>
               <l>Wyl vyce and ſyn depreſſe:</l>
               <l>Wyl cheafly loue the churche of God,</l>
               <l>And punyſh wickedneſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="37">
               <head>37</head>
               <l>The Lord almighty graunte that ſhee</l>
               <l>May proſpere to ſucceede:</l>
               <l>To haue on vs moaſt quiet raygne,</l>
               <l>And healp her in her neede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38">
               <pb facs="tcp:12538:6"/>
               <head>38</head>
               <l>The Lorde deſtroy her enemyes,</l>
               <l>And make her foes bewrayde:</l>
               <l>To bee ſoone catched in the ſnare,</l>
               <l>That they for her haue layde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="39">
               <head>39</head>
               <l>Defend her, Lord, and eke al thoſe,</l>
               <l>That beare to her good heart:</l>
               <l>And graunte that from thy holy word,</l>
               <l>She neuer ſwarue ne ſtart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40">
               <head>40</head>
               <l>Then doubtleſſe al, bothe old &amp; yong</l>
               <l>Shal prayſe thy name for euer:</l>
               <l>And ſing in Pſalmes to thee on earth,</l>
               <l>Which dooſt forſake vs neuer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="41">
               <head>41</head>
               <l>Lord ſaue our Queene moaſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe</l>
               <l>From euel and from feare:</l>
               <l>The Lady eke Elizabeth,</l>
               <l>Her godly ſiſter deare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42">
               <head>42</head>
               <l>Lord God preſerue the noble men,</l>
               <l>From daungers il and crime:</l>
               <l>And ſend vs peace and quietneſſe,</l>
               <l>In this ſame later tyme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="43">
               <head>43</head>
               <l>Al glory bee to God therfore,</l>
               <l>The father and the ſone:</l>
               <l>And alſo to the holy ghoſt,</l>
               <l>In deitye but one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44">
               <head>44</head>
               <l>As it hathe been from al beginninges</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12538:6"/>
               <l>Vnto this beefore:</l>
               <l>As now it is, and from this tyme,</l>
               <l>Shalbee for euermore.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="partial_metrical_Psalms">
               <head>¶ A godly Pſalme in meetre </head>
               <byline>by. T.B.</byline>
               <div type="partial_metrical_Psalm">
                  <head>Pſal. 145.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>1</head>
                     <l>O Prayſe the Lord (my ſoule and ſpreete)</l>
                     <l>So wyl I whyle I liue,</l>
                     <l>Yea, ſure as long as I remayne,</l>
                     <l>I wil him prayſes giue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2</head>
                     <l>Which healpeth them vnto their right,</l>
                     <l>That byde and ſuffre wrong,</l>
                     <l>That feedeth eke the hongry men,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe that thirſted long.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>3</head>
                     <l>The Lord from priſon loſeth men,</l>
                     <l>And giues the blynde their ſyght</l>
                     <l>The Lord doothe healp them vp that fal,</l>
                     <l>And loueth wel the right.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>4</head>
                     <l>He cares for ſtraungers, widowes hee</l>
                     <l>Defendes and fatherleſſe:</l>
                     <l>And ouerturnes the wayes of al</l>
                     <l>That worke vngodlyneſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="partial_metrical_Psalm">
                  <head>Pſal. 146.</head>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>5</head>
                     <l>The Lord ſettes vp and lifteth thoſe</l>
                     <l>That meeke in heart are founde:</l>
                     <l>And bringeth downe thungodly men</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12538:7"/>
                     <l>From highe vnto the grounde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <head>6</head>
                     <l>The legges of men delite him not,</l>
                     <l>Nor any horſes ſtrength</l>
                     <l>But thoſe that feare him, and doo truſt</l>
                     <l>To haue his grace at length.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="partial_metrical_Psalm">
                  <head>Pſal. 148.</head>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>7</head>
                     <l>O prayſe the Lord yee kinges &amp; people</l>
                     <l>Dwelling on the earth:</l>
                     <l>Yee Princes and yee iudges al,</l>
                     <l>Reioyce at ones for myrth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <head>8</head>
                     <l>Yong men and maydes, you aged men,</l>
                     <l>And children beeing yong,</l>
                     <l>Exalt his name, and alſo let</l>
                     <l>His praiſes bee your ſong.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>By Thomas Bownell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
